<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Meta on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</title>
    <link>http://maurodec.com/tags/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meta on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://maurodec.com/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross compiling Go applications</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often write blog posts on different computers. Sometimes I write on my
Macbook (which is where I run a local Hugo server to test things out), other
times I SSH into my Raspberry Pi and write there until I am on my Macbook
again. While writing my
&lt;a href=&#34;http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/&#34;&gt;Why I learned Python blog post&lt;/a&gt; I asked some friends
for feedback, however, I did not want to push an unfinished post to Github
Pages, so I decided to serve my Hugo blog from my Raspberry Pi. I soon realized
that I would have to install Hugo from source which could mean trouble&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating this Blog with Hugo</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes a bit funny how trends come and go in tech.
For a long time dynamic websites were seen as the way to go, no matter
for what kind of content. Lately a lot of people have gone back to
basics and (thankfully) decided to build their sites as a collection
of static pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started this blog I decided I did not want to go through the
hassle of maintaining a complex site and decided to use Hugo, a static
site generator. In this post I will talk about my experience building
my blog using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to my personal blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to have a place to write and express my thoughts for a while
now, so I figured I might as well start my own blog. My intention is to update
this as often as I can with posts about topics such as Software Engineering,
Programming or other interests of mine like Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>