<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</title>
    <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://maurodec.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Amet - Flattening a Python dictionary as environment variables</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had to build an ETL job in Python that was initially going to be
deployed on AWS. Little did I know that a last minute change from AWS to
Heroku would cause me to change how the job&amp;rsquo;s configuration was going to be
read significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross compiling Go applications</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often write blog posts on different computers. Sometimes I write on my
Macbook (which is where I run a local Hugo server to test things out), other
times I SSH into my Raspberry Pi and write there until I am on my Macbook
again. While writing my
&lt;a href=&#34;http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/&#34;&gt;Why I learned Python blog post&lt;/a&gt; I asked some friends
for feedback, however, I did not want to push an unfinished post to Github
Pages, so I decided to serve my Hugo blog from my Raspberry Pi. I soon realized
that I would have to install Hugo from source which could mean trouble&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I learned Python</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About eleven years ago, after finishing my first semester in University I
decided to learn how to program in Python. In this post I will talk about why I
found Python interesting at the time as well as how it felt to me as someone
with little programming knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating this Blog with Hugo</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes a bit funny how trends come and go in tech.
For a long time dynamic websites were seen as the way to go, no matter
for what kind of content. Lately a lot of people have gone back to
basics and (thankfully) decided to build their sites as a collection
of static pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started this blog I decided I did not want to go through the
hassle of maintaining a complex site and decided to use Hugo, a static
site generator. In this post I will talk about my experience building
my blog using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Handlers, Loopers, Message Queues and communication between Threads</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Android applications, as well as in applications with a GUI in general,
doing work in the background is essential as we do not want the UI to be
blocked by long running tasks that may cause it to appear to be frozen.
The Android Framework provides a simple but interesting mechanism for
communicating with background threads via the use of the &lt;code&gt;Message&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; classes. In this post I will attempt to explain not only how to use
them, but also how they relate to the &lt;code&gt;Looper&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;MessageQueue&lt;/code&gt;
classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple Material Design ripple effect for any iOS view</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I had to create a background color transition animation for an
iOS app I was working on. This animation was pretty similar to the ripple
effect Material Design buttons have. I thought it would be a fun idea to go
back and revise what I had done, change the animation so that it looks like the
Material Design ripple effect and create a UIView category with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post shows an implementation of this animation that can be applied to
any UIView.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to my personal blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to have a place to write and express my thoughts for a while
now, so I figured I might as well start my own blog. My intention is to update
this as often as I can with posts about topics such as Software Engineering,
Programming or other interests of mine like Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>