<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Blog - maurodec.com</title>
    <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Blog - maurodec.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://maurodec.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Thoughts: keep your tests simple</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/keep-tests-simple/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/keep-tests-simple/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing good tests, whether they are unit, acceptance, integration etc, is
hard. Few tests will run quickly but probably won&amp;rsquo;t cover much of the code,
however, having high coverage doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean your tests are good either.
The way tests are written also depends on what the software and it&amp;rsquo;s structure
is. Notwithstanding, there&amp;rsquo;s one aspect that I believe always helps,
simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Thoughts: Microsoft’s GitHub acquisition</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/microsoft-github-acquisition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/microsoft-github-acquisition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.github.com/2018-06-04-github-microsoft/&#34;&gt;It has recently been
announced&lt;/a&gt; that Microsoft
will be acquiring Github got USD 7.5b. The news was received by some with
dismay as Microsoft has historically been seen as a threat to Open Source
(Linux is a cancer, anyone?), while it was praised by others who consider
Microsoft has changed. What will the future hold for Github and Open Source?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Classes, namedtuples and __slots__</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/classes-namedtuples-slots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/classes-namedtuples-slots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Data types are needed in pretty much every program that needs to store and
manipulate data. These types usually have little to no behavior and simply
exist to keep track of information in a structured and orderly way. Recently,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0557/&#34;&gt;PEP 557 (Data Classes)&lt;/a&gt; was
accepted, however, it won&amp;rsquo;t appear until Python 3.7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Blog Post we will explore what options currently exist in Python 2.7
and 3.6 and how they differ from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text editors: which is the best?</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/best-text-editors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/best-text-editors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Text editors are probably the most basic tool of every software developer,
without them we would not be able to do our jobs. It makes sense then to try
and find out what the best text editor is, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it? Is it Vim? Is it Emacs?
Is it another? It&amp;rsquo;s important to first look at what we want in a text editor
before we are able to answer this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GDQ - Playing games for fun and charity</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/games-done-quick/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/games-done-quick/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, speedrunning is trying to finish a game as fast as possible.
There&amp;rsquo;s different set of rules for each game (called categories), but it always
boils down to how fast a game can be finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video games mean different things for different people. For some they are their
day-to-day source of entertainment or it&amp;rsquo;s their competitive nature that speaks
to them, while for others it may be childhood nostalgia. Whatever reason that
may be, GDQ, the seven day speedrunning marathon raises incredible amounts of
money for charity each year, and it only keeps on growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code smell and a lesson learned</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/side-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/side-effects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world there&amp;rsquo;s always time and resources available to refactor code
and to make sure it is as clean as possible. Even though it is well known that
refactoring code helps with maintainability and thus reduces development costs
in the long run, for various reasons refactoring does not always happen, or at
least not until things start to fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I will tell a little horror story that happened to me recently and
that could have been avoided if we had stopped to refactor the code we were
working on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amet - Flattening a Python dictionary as environment variables</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had to build an ETL job in Python that was initially going to be
deployed on AWS. Little did I know that a last minute change from AWS to
Heroku would cause me to change how the job&amp;rsquo;s configuration was going to be
read significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross compiling Go applications</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/cross-compile-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often write blog posts on different computers. Sometimes I write on my
Macbook (which is where I run a local Hugo server to test things out), other
times I SSH into my Raspberry Pi and write there until I am on my Macbook
again. While writing my
&lt;a href=&#34;http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/&#34;&gt;Why I learned Python blog post&lt;/a&gt; I asked some friends
for feedback, however, I did not want to push an unfinished post to Github
Pages, so I decided to serve my Hugo blog from my Raspberry Pi. I soon realized
that I would have to install Hugo from source which could mean trouble&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I learned Python</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/learning-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About eleven years ago, after finishing my first semester in University I
decided to learn how to program in Python. In this post I will talk about why I
found Python interesting at the time as well as how it felt to me as someone
with little programming knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating this Blog with Hugo</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/using-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes a bit funny how trends come and go in tech.
For a long time dynamic websites were seen as the way to go, no matter
for what kind of content. Lately a lot of people have gone back to
basics and (thankfully) decided to build their sites as a collection
of static pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started this blog I decided I did not want to go through the
hassle of maintaining a complex site and decided to use Hugo, a static
site generator. In this post I will talk about my experience building
my blog using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Handlers, Loopers, Message Queues and communication between Threads</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Android applications, as well as in applications with a GUI in general,
doing work in the background is essential as we do not want the UI to be
blocked by long running tasks that may cause it to appear to be frozen.
The Android Framework provides a simple but interesting mechanism for
communicating with background threads via the use of the &lt;code&gt;Message&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; classes. In this post I will attempt to explain not only how to use
them, but also how they relate to the &lt;code&gt;Looper&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;MessageQueue&lt;/code&gt;
classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple Material Design ripple effect for any iOS view</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I had to create a background color transition animation for an
iOS app I was working on. This animation was pretty similar to the ripple
effect Material Design buttons have. I thought it would be a fun idea to go
back and revise what I had done, change the animation so that it looks like the
Material Design ripple effect and create a UIView category with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post shows an implementation of this animation that can be applied to
any UIView.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to my personal blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to have a place to write and express my thoughts for a while
now, so I figured I might as well start my own blog. My intention is to update
this as often as I can with posts about topics such as Software Engineering,
Programming or other interests of mine like Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>