<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</title>
    <link>http://maurodec.github.io/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Blog - Mauro de Carvalho</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://maurodec.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple Material Design ripple effect for any iOS view</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.github.io/blog/ripple/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.github.io/blog/ripple/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I had to create a background color transition animation for an
iOS app I was working on. This animation was pretty similar to the ripple
effect Material Design buttons have. I thought it would be a fun idea to go
back and revise what I had done, change the animation so that it looks like the
Material Design ripple effect and create a UIView category with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post shows an implementation of this animation that can be applied to
any UIView.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;de-constructing-the-ripple-effect&#34;&gt;De-constructing the ripple effect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before implementing anything we have to know exactly what it is we have to
build. So first things first, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the ripple effect in slow motion.
For this, I set the animation scale for all animations on my phone to 20x and
recorded what happened when the flashlight tile is tapped in the quick settings
menu.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://maurodec.github.io/static/img/simpleripple/flashlight.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Ripple Effect in action&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The effect seems to be rather simple, a semi transparent circle starts
expanding where the tile was touched, only to start fading out before it
reaches its maximum size. If we take a closer look we can also see that the
expansion doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be uniform, it seems to expand rather quickly at
first and then slows down towards the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;constructing-the-ripple-effect&#34;&gt;Constructing the ripple effect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start writing any code we have to decide how we are going to be
implementing this. Is it going to be a subclass of a particular UIView? Is it
going to be a new type of UIView that we can add as a child? I opted for none
of these, instead I decided extending UIView with a category would be a
simple but effective idea. By creating a new category we can add this effect to
any UIView seamlessly and without any trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know where this is going to be coded we need to figure out an API
for this animation. For now this implementation will be uncomplicated.
For the animation there are a few things we need to define.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A position to serve as our starting point for our animation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The color we want our ripple to have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How big we want our ripple to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How fast we want it to expand, or rather, how long we want our animation to
last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the ripple should start fading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this post you can find a link to a repository holding all this
code, but lets see how to build this first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;code&gt;UIView&lt;/code&gt; Category will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;//gist.github.com/maurodec/08beefc7b8501f23b0afe59c53f89d75.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out animation will be taking place in a new &lt;code&gt;CAShapeLayer&lt;/code&gt;. This new layer will
sit behind all other layers so that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t cover any of the content of the
&lt;code&gt;UIView&lt;/code&gt;. We will then add a &lt;code&gt;CABasicAnimation&lt;/code&gt; that will transform a path.
This path will be the actual ripple, it will go from a tiny circle to the size
we specified as one of our parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simplified version of how to do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;//gist.github.com/maurodec/0b4c1989cab07dddb071046f91896121.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will do the same for the fade out effect in a similar manner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;//gist.github.com/maurodec/1de86b46518ace12e343a028adee9999.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, once we are done with our animations we can remove our ripple
animation from our &lt;code&gt;UIView&lt;/code&gt;. There is a small catch though. Normally we would
use a &lt;code&gt;CAAnimationDelegate&lt;/code&gt; and implement the appropriate callback, however we
would have to either store a reference to our newly added layer or we would
have to iterate through the sublayers and find the corresponding layer.
This would also mean we cannot (at least not easily) have more than one ripple
animation going at the same time. Thus we are going to go for a very simple
solution, we will enqueue a block of code to execute when the animations are
done and get rid of the ripple layer in that block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;//gist.github.com/maurodec/339ad058447bf491185e9c90ab5e36c3.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end-result&#34;&gt;The end result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/maurodec/SimpleRipple&#34;&gt;In this repository&lt;/a&gt; you can find the
full implementation along with an example application. The example consists of
two sliders that will control the ripple&amp;rsquo;s duration and radius and a button to
test it out. If you look closer (and not that closer, really) you can also see
that the two sliders will also show a ripple when they are touched.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://maurodec.github.io/static/img/simpleripple/ripple.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Example App&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you find any bugs or can think of improvements please feel free to submit
a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replicating what Google did with Material Design on iOS was rather
straightforward. The implementation is pretty short and easy to follow and
can be added to any application quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.github.io/blog/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.github.io/blog/helloworld/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to my personal blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to have a place to write and express my thoughts for a while
now, so I figured I might as well start my own blog. My intention is to update
this as often as I can with posts about topics such as Software Engineering,
Programming or other interests of mine like Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built this using the wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; site generator
which made everything surprisingly easy. I also handcrafted the blog theme from
scratch, thus, it is bound to change as time goes on and I realize things don&amp;rsquo;t
look as good as I had hoped or when they simply grow stale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your stay! 🖖🏼&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>