<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Source on Blog - maurodec.com</title>
    <link>http://maurodec.com/tags/open-source/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Source on Blog - maurodec.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://maurodec.com/tags/open-source/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Thoughts: Microsoft’s GitHub acquisition</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/microsoft-github-acquisition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/microsoft-github-acquisition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.github.com/2018-06-04-github-microsoft/&#34;&gt;It has recently been
announced&lt;/a&gt; that Microsoft
will be acquiring Github got USD 7.5b. The news was received by some with
dismay as Microsoft has historically been seen as a threat to Open Source
(Linux is a cancer, anyone?), while it was praised by others who consider
Microsoft has changed. What will the future hold for Github and Open Source?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amet - Flattening a Python dictionary as environment variables</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/amet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had to build an ETL job in Python that was initially going to be
deployed on AWS. Little did I know that a last minute change from AWS to
Heroku would cause me to change how the job&amp;rsquo;s configuration was going to be
read significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Android Handlers, Loopers, Message Queues and communication between Threads</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/android-handlers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Android applications, as well as in applications with a GUI in general,
doing work in the background is essential as we do not want the UI to be
blocked by long running tasks that may cause it to appear to be frozen.
The Android Framework provides a simple but interesting mechanism for
communicating with background threads via the use of the &lt;code&gt;Message&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; classes. In this post I will attempt to explain not only how to use
them, but also how they relate to the &lt;code&gt;Looper&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;MessageQueue&lt;/code&gt;
classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple Material Design ripple effect for any iOS view</title>
      <link>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://maurodec.com/blog/simple-ripple-effect-for-ios-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I had to create a background color transition animation for an
iOS app I was working on. This animation was pretty similar to the ripple
effect Material Design buttons have. I thought it would be a fun idea to go
back and revise what I had done, change the animation so that it looks like the
Material Design ripple effect and create a UIView category with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post shows an implementation of this animation that can be applied to
any UIView.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>